I promise I'm gonna focus and walk in this time.
Staying focused in today's world where everything is designed to distract you is harder than
ever.
And because of that, if you can stay focused for longer periods of time and
work smart, you'd be miles ahead of everyone else.
Use this video as a test for yourself.
If you can reach for the end without skipping it and really pay attention on
a deep level, you'd be in the minority.
Now, on top of all the distractions, imagine having ADHD, a neurological condition that makes
my brain wired for distraction by default.
But despite this, I found a system to stay hyper-focused and it helped me score
the top grade in my year at university, graduate from medical school, build my dream
YouTube community and now I'm working as a medical doctor in the UK.
So if it worked for my baseline distracted ADHD brain, hopefully it will definitely help
you whether you have ADHD or not.
Alright, let's start with point number one.
To achieve deep focus, which Cal Newport describes as a state of distraction-free concentration when
your brain works at its maximum potential, we need to take advantage of this golden
window of time of the day when our brain works the best.
This means working alongside our body's biological clock or circadian rhythm which controls when we
wake up in sleep and our peak energy times.
This chart shows the spectrum of biological clock so it ranges from extreme morning people
like myself to extreme night people.
I feel most awake and energised first thing in the morning so for me that
golden time of the day where being focused feels as effortless as it can get
is when I first wake up which is between 3 to 4am until I need
to get ready to go to work at 8am.
By the way, I'm aware that 3am wake up time is not usual, but this
is what feels natural to me and I've been like this since I've known myself.
That golden time of the day changes from person to person, so if you're an
extreme night owl on the opposite side of the spectrum and you feel most irritable
in the morning and work the best when everyone else sleeps, then I'd recommend you
to make use of night time rather than forcing yourself to wake up early.
Most people know by the time they become adults whether they're naturally a morning or
night person or somewhere in between.
But if you're not sure, think back and reflect on the times where you felt
in the zone and work seemed to flow effortlessly.
And once you identify that golden time of your day, build your work routine around
it to achieve the focus with minimal effort every day.
But difficult thing is if you're a night owl working a 9-5 job, this world
isn't designed for you.
Staying up late to work on your goals during your golden time isn't sustainable because
you still need to wake up early to get to your job.
If that's the case, you can watch my video on how to train your biological
clock to become more of a morning person.
And I've been working on something special for anyone who wants more evidence-based tips on
how to achieve deep focus.
So if you're interested, feel free to sign up for my free newsletter.
So the second strategy is to allow yourself to get bored and do nothing.
How do we achieve deep focus by purposefully doing nothing?
Sounds like a paradox, right?
Chris Bailey explains this phenomenon using this graph.
So we are in a hyper-stimulated state, constantly jumping between things that grab our attention.
But when we allow ourselves to feel boredom, we reduce that stimulation which in turn
expands our attention span and we return to work feeling more focused.
So he claims being bored actually has the same effect as reducing our phone use,
lowering that stimulation and improving focus.
And we know that when you let your brain rest and wander we activate something
called the default mode network.
This is a nerve pathway in our brain that becomes active when we're at wakeful
rest, like when we're daydreaming or spacing out in the shower or just being bored
in the car in traffic, which is hard these days because of digital entertainment available
24-7.
Research surrounding this is really recent and not fully known, but what we know is
there is a dynamic interplay between default mode network that gets activated when we're bored
and the executive network, which is involved in focusing and working through tasks.
So the idea is to find space in our schedules to activate this default mode
network, rediscover boredom, have a disconnection ritual from the digital world.
Even if it's for a few minutes, lay on the couch and see where your
mind goes.
You know, Einstein was known for daydreaming and using his daydreams to develop his theories.
So doing nothing is actually doing something.
This is generally when we find those breakthrough moments.
I know I personally come up with the most interesting thoughts when I'm in the
shower.
Plus, it helps reduce our stimulation, so use boredom as a tool to become more
focused.
Now we come to insanely simple but hardest to practice number three, phone fasting.
For many of us, whether we admit it or not, social media and phone use
has become a kind of addiction.
Breaking this habit and creating a healthy relationship with our devices requires effort.
American Psychological Association says when we're sitting in front of a computer, especially when our
phone is nearby, we focus on one thing for 40 seconds before we switch to
something else.
It's because when our phone is in sight or even when we know it's nearby,
we experience something called the anticipatory dopamine.
By the way, dopamine is a chemical in our brain that enables us to take
action and get motivated.
Just seeing your phone or the thought of checking your phone triggers a dopamine response.
Like, your brain knows Instagram is just within reach.
Classic example of this is walking into a grocery shop, seeing the junk food aisle
and thinking, Ooh, I might want those crisps.
So hide your phone away whilst working or leave it in another room.
During my medical school exams, I was so desperate that I used to give my
phone to my flatmate, because it's like she's holding me accountable.
Putting your phone on airplane mode or do not disturb is also effective because our
brain responds to cues so just seeing an email or notification pop up can spike
your dopamine making it harder to focus.
I feel like society just got trained in lust and hate that notifications need to
be part of our lives but I personally do not have my notifications on for
any social media accounts like Instagram, TikTok, Snapchat.
In the end, we're all so trained to open these apps by the habits of
dopamine that we're unlikely to miss anything important.
You're always going to open WhatsApp and Insta DMs that you don't need to be
told that it's there.
If you just turn everything off it empowers you.
Now you're in control of the timing of your notifications rather than it being in
control of you.
Fourth, don't attempt to multitask.
When you try to multitask you're not actually doing more than one activity at a
time, instead your brain rapidly switches focus from one thing to another.
This constant switching uses up brain's main energy source, oxygenated glucose, which is basically sugar
attached to oxygen, and it's the exact thing your brain needs to stay focused.
As a result, multitasking can lead to faster mental tiredness and reduce productivity.
Instead, focus on one thing at a time by prioritising your work and start with
the most important, urgent tasks and work your way through the list, rather than overwhelming
yourself.
So how can we actually train our brains to focus for longer?
As you improve the skill of deep work, it becomes easier to stay focused for
longer rather than taking mini breaks in between.
And it's because of this phenomenon in physics called the activation energy.
Is the initial effort or mental energy needed to start focusing on a task?
Once you've started, staying concentrated becomes easier because you build momentum.
When you first start training this skill, you might prefer using Pomodoro technique.
So 20 minute work, then 10 minute break.
But as you progress, you can increase the time you work consistently to 30 minutes,
then 40 minutes and eventually hours once you master the skill of deep focus.
Then, rather than using a countdown, you can use a stopwatch instead.
Now it's an endurance test against yourself, and you can track your progress and see
how long you can be in this zone
before a brain fog starts to set in.
This way, you won't need to take breaks as often, and I prefer not to,
to prevent overcoming that activation energy all over again.
If you want to hear more from me, sign up for our free newsletter, and
to learn how to become more of a morning person and train your biological clock
click on this video bye